Finding Aid for the Lejaren Hiller Collection of Compositional Flow Charts, circa 1968-1987
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Lejaren Hiller Collection of Compositional Flow Charts, circa 1968-1987
Mus. Arc. 5.3
Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994
3 map drawers, 1 box
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Flow charts created for computer music composition by Lejaren Hiller and included as figures and illustrations in his published articles about the processes used in writing computer music, including his works, HPSCHD, Algorithms I and Algorithms III. The collection also contains unidentified flow charts and diagrams, as well as negatives of other charts created by Hiller.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Hiller.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Lejaren Hiller was born on February 23, 1924, in New York City. He received his B.A., M.A., and Ph.D. in chemistry from Princeton University, where he also studied music theory and composition with Milton Babbitt and Roger Sessions. In 1958, Hiller received his M.Mus. from the University of Illinois where he founded the Experimental Music Studio.
In 1957, Hiller collaborated with Leonard Isaacson on the Illiac Suite, the first significant use of a computer in composition. The Illiac Suite (String Quartet No. 4) was so named for the Illiac computer on which the calculations for the score parameters were made. Hiller was able to tap the power of the Illiac for the generation and selection of large quantities of random values in a fundamental type of stochastic modeling known as "the Monte Carlo Method."
Lejaren Hiller's importance to the field of computer music cannot be over-emphasized. His work on the use of computers for the generation of musical parameters such as pitch, rhythm, duration, etc. in pieces of music using traditional instruments, opened a door to new methods of music material generation and simultaneously to the computer-assisted analysis of the process of music composition.
Scope and Content Note
Compositional flow charts produced by Lejaren Hiller. The collection consists of 106 flow charts housed in map drawers, and 18 other items in individual folders housed in a flat box. While each item is dated, the dates are approximate based on when the corresponding article authored by Hiller was published. Some items do not contain a corresponding article figure number as Hiller added the number in the article at the time of publication.
When the flow charts were received by the Music Library, they arrived rolled up. After long-term storage, the glue on many of the instructional labels dried out so the labels detached from the charts when they were straightened. Restoration work was completed for an exhibit showcasing the flow charts, wherein many of the labels were reattached. However, a few of the flow charts remain incomplete because it has not been possible to identify the correct positions of the detached labels. In order to preserve each of the flow charts, they have been cleaned by the preservation department and encapsulated in mylar.
A few flow charts also have corresponding photographic negatives. These negatives are filed, where appropriate, immediately following the original flow chart. For some figures only the negative exists, and it has been filed in place of the missing original.
Arrangement
The collection's series are arranged chronologically by the publication date of each corresponding article. Within each series, the items are arranged according to their location within the article written by Lejaren Hiller. Please note that Items 1-110 have no box indication because the items are stored in map case drawers.
I. Flowcharts and diagrams found in Computer Programs Used to Produce the Composition HPSCHD
II. Flowcharts and diagrams found in Phrase Generation in Computer Music Composition
III. Flow Charts and Diagrams used in Composing the Second Movement of Algorithms III.
IV. Flow charts and Diagrams used in Computer Programs Used to Produce the Composition Algorithms I
V. Unmatched Flow Charts and Diagrams
VI. Additional Graphs, Diagrams and Flow Charts
VII. Photocopies of Flow Charts Found in Other Articles
Container List
- Flow charts and diagrams found in Computer Programs Used to Produce the Composition HPSCHD. Technical Report No. 4, National Science Foundation Project No. GK-14191, August, 1972, I.; Items 1-39
  Items are arranged according to where they appear in the article.
  - Figure 4: Sub-Routine ICHING, p. 15, 1 flow chart 34 cm. x 43 cm. (Item 1)
  - Figure 6: Sub-Routine ML3DST, p. 18, 1 flow chart 31 cm. x 24 cm. (Item 2)
  - Figure 2: First Page of Notentafel, p. 28, 1 score 31 cm. x 23 cm. (Item 3)
  - Sub-Routine WURFEL, p. 31, 1 negative 32 cm. x 22 cm. (Item 4)
  - Figure 5: Program DICE GAME, p. 34, 1 flow chart 28 cm. x 54 cm. (Item 5)
  - Figure 6: First Eight Bars of "Passes," Solo II, p. 41, 1 score 31 cm. x 61 cm. (Item 6)
  - Figure 7: First Eight Bars of "Passes," Solo IV, p. 42, 1 score 31 cm. x 61 cm. (Item 7)
  - Figure 2.1: Simplified Block Diagram for Main Program, p. 46, 1 flow chart 39 cm. x 56 cm. (Item 8)
  - Simplified Block Diagram for Main Program, p. 46, 1 flow chart negative in 2 pieces 23 cm. x 29 cm. (Item 9)
  - Figure 2.8: Main Program, Part 1, p. 64, 1 flow chart 37 cm. x 14 cm. (Item 10)
  - Figure 2.9: Main Program, Part 2, p. 67, 1 flow chart 50 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 11)
  - Figure 2.10: Main Program, Part 3, p. 70, 1 flow chart 50 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 12)
  - Figure 2.11: Main Program, Part 4, p. 72, 1 flow chart 51 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 13)
  - Figure 2.12: Main Program, Part 5, p. 75, 1 flow chart 37 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 14)
  - Figure 2.13: Main Program, Part 6, p. 77, 1 flow chart 51 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 15)
  - Figure 2.14: Main Program, Part 7, p. 80, 1 flow chart 56 cm. x 39 cm. (Item 16)
  - Flow chart for Main Program, p. 80, 1 flow chart negative, in 7 pieces (Item 17)
  - Figure 3.2: Sub-Routine ML3DST, p. 102, 1 negative 33 cm. x 26 cm. (Item 18)
  - Figure 3.3: Sub-Routine SHUFFL, p. 106, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 29 cm. (Item 19)
  - Figure 3.4: Sub-Routine REIHE, p. 110, 1 flow chart 41 cm. x 29 cm. (Item 20)
  - Sub-Routine REIHE, p. 110, 1 negative 31 cm. x 21 cm. (Item 21)
  - Figure 3.5: Diatonic Scales Produced by Sub-Routine MODE, p. 112, 1 score 23 cm. x 31 cm. (Item 22)
  - Figure 3.6: Sub-Routine MODE, p. 116, 1 flow chart 40 cm. x 26 cm. (Item 23)
  - Sub-Routine MODE, p. 116, 1 negative 30 cm. x 20 cm. (Item 24)
  - Figure 3.7: Two Examples of Sets of Goals Produced by Sub-Routine CANTO, p. 119, 1 score 23 cm. x 31 cm. (Item 25)
  - Figure 3.8: Sub-Routine CANTO, p. 125, 1 flow chart 46 cm. x 33 cm. (Item 26)
  - Sub-Routine CANTO, 1 negative 35 cm. x 25 cm. (Item 27)
  - Figure 3.9: Melodic Line Produced by Sub-Routine CHOOSE, p. 128, 1 score 23 cm. x 31 cm. (Item 28)
  - Figure 3.10: Sub-Routine CHOOSE, p. 137, 1 flow chart 41 cm. x 42 cm. (Item 29)
  - Sub-Routine "ML.RL1", p. 141 1972, 1 flow chart 29 cm. x 21 cm. (Item 30)
  - Sub-Routine "ML.RL1" 1972, 1 negative 28 cm. x 21 cm. (Item 31)
  - Typical ornament produce by ORMOLU, p. 146, 1 graph 18 cm. x 19 cm. (Item 32)
  - Figure 3.13: Sub-Routine ORMOLU, p. 151, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 50 cm. (Item 33)
  - The Triangular Grid Used to Compute Inflection Points by Sub-Routine TIMBRE, p. 155, 1 graph 29 cm. x 27 cm. (Item 34)
  - Sub-Routine DIGANS, p. 175, 1 flow chart, 73 cm. x 68 cm. (Item 35)
  - Sub-Routine DIGANS, 1 flow chart negative, in 4 pieces (Item 36)
  - Figure 4.2: Flow Charts for Sub-Routines that Transfer Data for Illiac II, p. 185, 1 flow chart 44 cm. x 54 cm. (Item 37)
  - Flow Charts for Subroutines that Transfer Data for Illiac II, 1 flow chart negative 24 cm. x 27 cm. (Item 38)
  - Figure 4.6: Program "Knobs", p. 202, 1 flow chart 19 cm. x 36 cm. (Item 39)
- Flow charts and diagrams found in Phrase Generation in Computer Music Composition, Technical Report No. 10, National Science Foundation GK-14191, October, 1978, II.; Items 40-57
  - Figure 3.1: Basic Plan of Program PHRASE, p. 19, 1 flow chart 28 cm. x 22 cm. (Item 40)
  - Figure 3.3: Program PHRASE, Expanded, p. 25, 1 flow chart 56 cm. x 41 cm. (Item 41)
  - Figure 3.3: Col. 1, p. 27, 1 flow chart, 57 cm. x 23 cm., incomplete (Item 42)
  - Figure 3.3: Col. 2-3, p. 29, 1 flow chart 49 cm. x 27 cm. (Item 43)
  - Figure 3.3: Col. 4-5, p. 32, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 23 cm. (Item 44)
  - Figure 3.3: Col. 6-7, p. 34, 1 flow chart 44 cm. x 33 cm. (Item 45)
  - Figure 3.3: Col. 8-10, p. 37, 1 flow chart 54 cm. x 26 cm. (Item 46)
  - Figure 5.2: Sub-Routine ZIPF, p. 54, 1 flow chart 33 cm. x 24 cm. (Item 47)
  - Figure 5.3: Sub-Routine THEME, p. 57, 1 flow chart 28 cm. x 22 cm. (Item 48)
  - Figure 5.4: Sub-Routine READL, p. 61, 1 flow chart 53 cm. x 89 cm. (Item 49)
  - Figure 5.6: Sub-Routine FILL, p. 68, 1 flow chart 55 cm. x 86 cm. (Item 50)
  - Figure 5.7: Sub-Routine PITCH, p. 75, 1 flow chart, 62 cm. x 54 cm., incomplete (Item 51)
  - Figure 5.8: Sub-Routine MODE, p. 79, 1 flow chart 45 cm. x 29 cm. (Item 52)
  - Figure 5.9: Sub-Routine GOAL, p. 82, 1 flow chart 44 cm. x 31 cm. (Item 53)
  - Figure 5.10: Sub-Routine MLRL1, p. 85, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 37 cm. (Item 54)
  - Figure 5.11: Sub-Routine MLRL2, p. 89, 1 flow chart, 43 cm. x 55 cm., incomplete (Item 55)
  - Figure 5.12: Sub-Routine RHYTHM, p. 94, 1 flow chart 44 cm. x 21 cm. (Item 56)
  - Figure 7.1: Persiflage, p. 143, 1 flow chart, 22 cm. x 28 cm., incomplete (Item 57)
- Flow Charts and Diagrams used in Composing the Second Movement of Algorithms III, Technical Report No. 12, National Science Foundation Project No. GK-14191, February, 1980, III.; Items 58-61
  - Figure 3.3: Chance of Phrase Surviving, p. 28, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 58)
  - Figure 3.4: Phase Assembly, p. 29, 1 flow chart 87 cm. x 48 cm. (Item 59)
  - Figure 3.5: Double Imitation, p. 36, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 30 cm. (Item 60)
  - Figure 3.6: First Tone-Row Sequence, p. 40, 1 flow chart 58 cm. x 45 cm. (Item 61)
- Flow charts and Diagrams used in Computer Programs Used to Produce the Composition Algorithms I, Technical Report No. 13, 1983, IV.; Items 62-97
  - Figure 2.1: Block Diagram of "The Decay of Information", p. 14, 1 flow chart 28 cm. x 40 cm. (Item 62)
  - Figure 2.3: Sub-Routine GOV, p. 23, 1 flow chart 52 cm. x 38 cm. (Item 63)
  - Figure 2.4: Flow Chart for Sub-Routine DIST, p. 33, 1 flow chart 58 cm. x 56 cm. (Item 64)
  - Figure 2.6: Flow Chart for Sub-Routine "ML.ORD", p. 45, 1 flow chart 59 cm. x 36 cm. (Item 65)
  - Figure 2.7: Unit Storage Plan of Individual Note Parameters Employing Split Storage Locations, p. 51, 1 chart 22 cm. x 22 cm. (Item 66)
  - Figure 2.9: Storage Array for Fourth-Order Transition Probabilities, p. 53, 1 chart 30 cm. x 22 cm. (Item 67)
  - Figure 3.2: Block Diagram for the Programming of "Icosahedron", p. 101, 1 flow chart 38 cm. x 14 cm. (Item 68)
  - Figure 3.6: Main Program for "Icosahedron" (Part 1), p. 123, 1 flow chart 58 cm. x 51 cm. (Item 69)
  - Figure 3.7: "Icosahedron": Flow Chart IV: Generating Pitch and Dynamics Rows, p. 129, 1 flow chart 53 cm. x 59 cm. (Item 70)
  - Figure 3.8: Main Program for "Icosahedron" (Part 3), p. 133, 1 flow chart 47 cm. x 57 cm. (Item 71)
  - Figure 3.9: Production of Remaining Note Parameters, p. 139, 1 flow chart 59 cm. x 74 cm. (Item 72)
  - Figure 3.9: Production of Remaining Note Parameters (Part 2), p. 139, 1 flow chart, 59 cm. x 37 cm., incomplete (Item 73)
  - Figure 3.10: Main Program Section FC7, p. 147 1983, 1 flow chart 54 cm. x 74 cm. (Item 74)
  - Figure 3.12: Sub-Routine MATCH, p. 159, 1 flow chart 56 cm. x 47 cm. (Item 75)
  - Figure 4.3.1: Instrumentation Plan for Part 1B of "The Incorporation of Constraints", p. 178, 1 graph 22 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 76)
  - Figure 4.3.2: Macros of Program M3SIB, p. 181, 1 flow chart 39 cm. x 26 cm. (Item 77)
  - Figure 4.3.3: Main Program for M3SIB, p. 184, 1 flow chart 38 cm. x 40 cm. (Item 78)
  - Figure 4.3.4: Sub-Routine ML.CDC, 192, 1 flow chart 42 cm. x 30 cm. (Item 79)
  - Figure 4.3.5: Two Examples of Interval Computation in Subroutine ML.CDC, p. 198, 1 chart 28 cm. x 23 cm. (Item 80)
  - Figure 4.4.1: Variance of Consonance and Dissonance in the Four "Versions" of Part 3A of "The Incorporation of Constraints", p. 204, 1 graph 22 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 81)
  - Figure 4.4.2: Macros of Program M3S2A, p. 206, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 46 cm. (Item 82)
  - Figure 4.4.3: Main Program for M3S2A, p. 211, 1 flow chart 38 cm. x 58 cm. (Item 83)
  - Figure 4.5.1: Seven Macros of Program M3S2B, p. 218, 1 flow chart 38 cm. x 45 cm. (Item 84)
  - Figure 4.5.2: Main Program for M3S2B, p. 222, 1 flow chart, 34 cm. x 41 cm., incomplete (Item 85)
  - Figure 4.5.4: Sub-Routine ML.RL2, p. 231, 1 flow chart 42 cm. x 27 cm. (Item 86)
  - Figure 4.5.5: Sub-Routine ML.RL3, p. 235, 1 flow chart 45 cm. x 47 cm. (Item 87)
  - Figure 4.6.1: Macros for Program M3S3A, p. 243, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 35 cm. (Item 88)
  - Figure 4.6.2: Program M3S3A, p. 247, 1 flow chart, 43 cm. x 56 cm. incomplete (Item 89)
  - Figure 4.7: Program M3S3B, p. 253, 1 flow chart 46 cm. x 47 cm. (Item 90)
  - Figure 4.8.1: Four Macros of Program M3S4A, p. 258, 1 flow chart 28 cm. x 46 cm. (Item 91)
  - Figure 4.8.2: Main Program of M3S4A, p. 259, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 92)
  - Figure 4.9: Program M3S4B, p. 272, 1 flow chart 37 cm. x 46 cm. (Item 93)
  - Figure 4.10.1: DO MACRO and Main Routine of M3S5A, p. 276, 1 flow chart, 28 cm. x 43 cm., incomplete (Item 94)
  - Figure 4.11.1: Macros of Program M3S5B, p. 281, 1 flow chart 45 cm. x 50 cm. (Item 95)
  - Figure 4.11.2: Main Program M3S5B, p. 286, 1 flow chart 45 cm. x 26 cm. (Item 96)
  - Figure 4.11.3: Sub-Routine ML4DST, p. 291, 1 flow chart 37 cm. x 27 cm. (Item 97)
- Unmatched Flow Charts and Diagrams, undated, V.; Items 98-110
  Items are arranged according to the figure numbers present on each item.
  - Figure 1: Condensed Flow Chart for Sub-Routine STOCH - Part 3 - Making a Stochastic Choice, 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 37 cm. (Item 98)
  - Figure 2.3.1: New Play-Rest Functions in Branch 4 of Sub-Routine BRANCH, 1 flow chart 52 cm. x 24 cm. (Item 99)
  - Figure 3.4.1: Parts 1 and 2 of Sub-Routine REIHE: Row Generation and Shuffle, 1 flow chart 39 cm. x 32 cm. incomplete (Item 100)
  - Figure 3.4.2: Condensed Flow Chart of Part 3 of Sub-Routine REIHE: Serial Phrase Assembly, 1 flow chart 34 cm. x 19 cm. incomplete (Item 101)
  - Figure 3.4.3: Part _ of Sub-Routine REIHE, column headings, 1 flow chart 18 cm. x 44 cm. incomplete (Item 102)
  - Figure 3.4.3: Part _ of Sub-Routine REIHE, columns 1-3, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 57 cm. incomplete (Item 103)
  - Figure 3.4.3: Part _ of Sub-Routine REIHE, column 4, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 17 cm. incomplete (Item 104)
  - Figure 3.4.4: Part 4 of Sub-Routine REIHE: Serial Checkoff, 1 flow chart 44 cm. x 36 cm. incomplete (Item 105)
  - Figure 7: Part 3 of Sub-Routine STOCH: Choosing New Note Parameters, 1 flow chart 51 cm. x 58 cm. incomplete (Item 106)
  - Figure 8: Part 4 of Sub-Routine STOCH: Storage of a Successful Choice, 1 flow chart 46 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 107)
  - Figure 9: Part 4 of Sub-Routine STOCH: Printout of the KFREQ Array, 1 flow chart 46 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 108)
  - Flowchart for Composing, Orchestrating and Converting to Tape, 1 flow chart 43 cm. x 34 cm. (Item 109)
  - "System for Analysis and Synthesis of Sounds at SUNY, Buffalo", 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 28 cm. (Item 110)
- Additional Graphs, Diagrams and Flow Charts undated, VI.; Items 111-116
  - Trial Distribution of Stochastic Orders Produced by Subroutine "Govern", 1 graph 20 cm. x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 111)
  - Schematic Outline of Computer System for Analysis and Synthesis of Sounds at SUNY Buffalo, 1 diagram 22 cm. x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 112)
  - Figures from an unknown article on electronic music, 15 graphs 15 leaves, some photocopies, handwritten notes on tracing paper overlays (Box 1, Item 113)
    Figure 2.1 (a,b,c)
    Figure 2.2 (a,b,c)
    Figure 2.3 (a,b)
    Figure 2.4 (a,b,c)
    Figure 2.5
    Figure 2.6 (a,b,c)
    Figure 2.7
    Figure 2.8
    Figure 2.9
    Figure 2.10
    Figure 2.11
    Figure 2.12
    Figure 2.13
    Figure 2.14 (a,b)
    Figure 3.1
  - Tables and figures relating to stochastic choices, 1 flow chart, 5 tables 6 items (Box 1, Item 114)
    Figure 6. Parts 1 and 2 of Subroutine STOCH: Input Sequences
    Figure 2. The Storage Plan of the KFREQ Storage Array in Subroutine "STOCH"
    Table 2.9.1: Definitions of Stochastic Processes
    Table 2.9.2: The Five Sections of Subroutine STOCH
    Table 2.9.3: Transition Probabilities for Stochastic Processes
    Table 2.9.4: Storage Allocation for Stochastic Choice Processes
    Table 2.9.5: Formulas for Entering the KFREQ Array
    Table 2.9.6: Currently Available Distribution Subroutines
  - Comparison of Three Different Distribution Subroutines, 1 graph 28 cm. x 22 cm. (Box 1, Item 115)
  - Loose Flow Chart Pieces, 1 folder; Envelope containing all unidentified flow chart labels. (Box 1, Item 116)
- Photocopies of Flow Charts Found in Other Articles, 1968-1987, VII.; Items 117-121
  - Portion of HPSCHD Program, 1968, 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 28 cm.; HPSCHD Interview by Larry Austin in Source 2, 17 (Box 1, Item 117)
  - Figure 3: Flow chart for Subroutine "MATCH", 1969, 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 28 cm.; Some Compositional Techniques Involving the Use of Computers in Music by Computers, 78 (Box 1, Item 118)
  - Sub-Routine "ICHING", 1970, 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 28 cm.; Programming the I-Ching Oracle in Computer Studies in the Humanities and Verbal Behavior, 138 (Box 1, Item 119)
  - Subroutine ICHING, December, 1986, 1 flow chart 22 cm. x 28 cm.; On Composing Music With Computers in Colóquio artes, 62 (Box 1, Item 120)
  - Subroutine "WURFEL"; Program DICEGAME, 1987, 2 flow charts 22 cm. x 28 cm.; Sulla programmazione del gioco musicale dei dadi di Mozart in Profili del Suono (1987) (Box 1, Item 121)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994--Archives; Computer music; Electronic music; Flow charts
Genres
flow charts
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Lejaren Hiller Archive
Mus. Arc. 5
Music manuscripts, including sketches, program notes, correspondence, writings, recordings, and photographs.
Preserving Lejaren A. Hiller's Flow charts: A Case Study
Online exhibit summary about the restoration and preservation of the flow charts. The exhibit demonstrates why the preservation was required and what it entailed, with historical background on the use of flow charts in the creation of computer music and Hiller's role as musical innovator in the realm of electronic music
Lejaren A. Hiller: Computer Music Pioneer
Online exhibit summary about Lejaren Hiller utilizing materials from the Lejaren Hiller Archive.